<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full and true account of His Grace Duke Schomberg's marching towards Dublin and of the preparations the late King James is making to oppose him with other affairs relating to Ireland : in a letter from Chester, Sept. 2.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R235824</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13744720</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13744720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 454:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full and true account of His Grace Duke Schomberg's marching towards Dublin and of the preparations the late King James is making to oppose him with other affairs relating to Ireland : in a letter from Chester, Sept. 2.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Green ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, Sept. 4th, 1689; J.F."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schomberg, Friedrich Hermann Schomberg, --  Duke of, 1615-1690.</term>
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101694:1"/>
            <head>A Full and True ACCOUNT OF HIS <hi>Grace Duke Schomberg's</hi> Marching Towards DUBLIN, AND Of the Preparations the late King <hi>James</hi> is making to oppoſe him: With other Affairs relating to <hi>Ireland:</hi> In a Letter from <hi>Cheſter, Sept.</hi> 2.</head>
            <div type="license">
               <p>Licenſed,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Sept. 4th. 1689.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>J. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="body_of_letter">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Cheſter, <date>
                        <hi>Sept.</hi> 2d. 1689.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce my laſt we have this farther Account of <hi>Carrick-Fergus,</hi> That before the Surrender of the place, Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> having advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Trenches, and ſeveral Breaches being made by the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non from the Frigats to the Sea-wards, and the Bombs having done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable damage by Land, upon the Town, the Enemies Hearts begun to fail, and beat a Parley; upon which ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably advancing to capitulate, the treacherous <hi>Iriſh</hi> fired upon them, and killed near Sixty of our Men; upon which Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> declared, He would give none of them Quarter; but being informed ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Proteſtants were there in durance, and having compaſſion for them, gave them the Terms mentioned in my laſt, and conveyed them Three Miles from the Town, which was as far as he was obliged; but they had not marched above Three Miles further, when the <hi>Scotch</hi> of the Country, even the Women, fell upon them, the former diſarming them, the latter recovered what they had plundered them of before, and ſo let them go towards <hi>Charlemont;</hi> which place his Grace Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> intends to take in, being upon his March towards <hi>Dublin,</hi> having only the <hi>Newry</hi>-Paſs, and <hi>Drogheda</hi> to take; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> daily imploring his Protection as he marches. The <hi>Enniskilling</hi> Party have over-run all <hi>Connaught,</hi> except <hi>Athloan</hi> and <hi>Gallaway,</hi> which is indeed a ſtrong place.</p>
               <p>By a Veſſel arrived at <hi>Liverpool,</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> laſt, who left <hi>Dublin</hi> the Week before, being a Ship of Mr. <hi>Thomas Bell</hi>'s, an eminent Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and a good Proteſtant, wherein was his Wife, and ſome other Paſſengers, who bring this Account, That before they came
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101694:2"/> away, that ſeveral Mutinies had happened, and of their being a mortal Feud between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in which Eleven <hi>French</hi> were killed upon the place. The fine Wood at <hi>Santrey,</hi> and at <hi>Clantarfe</hi> are all cut down, and the Ways palliſadoed between <hi>Swords</hi> and <hi>Dublin;</hi> and that K. <hi>James</hi> threatens to fight the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army between <hi>Drogheda</hi> and <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and intends to march his Army thither, having fortified the Town of <hi>Drogheda</hi> with all the care and diligence they are capable of; which truly is not much, for a ſafe Retreat in caſe the Army ſhould be beaten, thinking that may endure a Winter-Siege, and then they may be Reliev'd by the <hi>French</hi> at Spring; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> bragging. That they have left the <hi>North</hi> for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to make themſelves Graves, and to prevent all Surprize, and make ſure of themſelves. King <hi>James,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nobility by his Example, have ordered all their beſt Moveables, together with Ammunition and Artillery, to the ſtrong Garriſon of <hi>Athloam,</hi> it being near the Center of the Kingdom, where they have laid up a Magazine, and made one Coll. <hi>Grace,</hi> an old <hi>Iriſh</hi> Collonel in the laſt Rebellion, Governour; who hath already ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plundered the parts adjacont: This place the late King believes to be beſt for an Eſcape to <hi>Gallaway,</hi> and ſo ſhip off for <hi>France;</hi> but juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came away, we heard it reported <hi>Gallaway</hi> had declared for K. <hi>William:</hi> So that he hath veſted <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> again with the Government; and it is ſaid they are to act ſeparately with diſtinct Armies; and by his Interceſſion have enlarged all the Proteſtants, except Four, and thoſe who have heretofore behaved themſelves with the greateſt Inſolence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, do now careſs them after an extraordinary manner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to <hi>Goſhop</hi> it after the <hi>Iriſh</hi> way, <hi>Dear Joy: I am ſure I did you no wrong; I was always your Friend, and ſpake for you well every-where.</hi> But God grant that upon their deſerting of <hi>Dublin</hi> they do not burn it; and indeed there is a great deal of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Intereſt in the Houſes of that City, which we hope may be a means to preſerve it. There was one Mr. <hi>Swine</hi> Governour of <hi>Carrick-Fergus,</hi> when taken, and not <hi>Mark Talbot, Tyrconnel</hi>'s Baſtard-Son, as was reported.</p>
               <p>Coll. <hi>Villiers</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe is gone to <hi>High-Lake</hi> to be ſhipped off; and my Lord <hi>Hewit</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe likewiſe comes into <hi>Cheſter</hi> this day, in order to follow; there being all the Care imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble taken to haſten them. Farewel till farther—I forgot to tell you, that the Proteſtants <hi>Britiſh,</hi> Repair into <hi>Ireland</hi> in great Numbers, with all alacrity and chearfulneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>REaſons why the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> cannot comply with the Late King <hi>James's</hi> Proclamation, ſent lately to that Kingdom, and Proſecuted by the Late Viſcount <hi>Dundee.</hi>Containing an Anſwer to every Paragraph of the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation; and vindicating the ſaid Parliament their preſent Proceedings againſt him. Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Green</hi> near <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
